Guide to the Allison Davis Papers 1932-1984
University of Chicago Library
- Series VI: Writings
  - Subseries 4: Articles
    - "Identity Problems in Young Children," reprint, undated (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - "Independence and Identity," manuscript, undated (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - "Language, Intelligence, and Academic Achievement," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - "Language and Social-Class Perspectives," manuscripts, notes, 1963 (Box 79, Folder 7-8)
    - "Language and Social-Class Perspectives," Basil Bernstein, "Language and Social Class," "Restricted and Elaborated Codes," reprint, manuscript, notes, 1960 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - "The Measurement of Mental Systems," with Robert J. Havighurst, reprint, memorandum, 1948 (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - "The New Teacher in the Inner-City School," manuscript, undated (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - "Parent and Adolescent Offspring," manuscript, undated (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - "Personality and Social Mobility," reprint, undated (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - "Poor But Able," manuscripts, undated (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - "Psychological, Social, and Cultural Antecedents of Intellectual Disability and Concomitant Social Disability," manuscript, undated (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - "The School in the Social Order," outlines, undated (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - "Social-Class Influences Upon Learning," reprint, 1948 (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - "Socialization and Adolescent Personality," manuscript, reprints, 1944 (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - "Survival and Defense Systems of Slum-Life," manuscript, undated (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - "Teaching the Culturally Disadvantaged Pupil," manuscripts, undated (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - "Teaching Language and Reading to Disadvantaged Negro Children," manuscripts, reprint, notes, 1967 (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - "White and Black," outline, notes, ca. 1963 (Box 80, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 5: Lectures
    - "Adolescence and Growing Up," manuscripts, undated (Box 80, Folder 15)
    - "The Age of Anger and Fear," Three Hundred and Thirty-second Convocation, University of Chicago, manuscripts, convocation booklet, notes, 1970 (Box 80, Folder 16)
    - "Education for the Conservation of the Human Resources of the United States," American Association of School Administrators, press release, 1949 (Box 80, Folder 17)
    - "Identity and Struggle for Independence," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 80, Folder 18)
    - "Identity in Adolescence and Young Adulthood," Leo Franklin Lecture, Wayne State University, manuscripts, notes, 1966 (Box 80, Folder 19)
    - "The Middle-Class Pupil and His Family," Parent's Association of the Laboratory School, manuscript, undated (Box 80, Folder 20)
    - "The Negro and Schools," partial manuscript, notes, clipping, 1964 (Box 80, Folder 21)
    - "Psychology of the Child in the Middle Class," Horace Mann Lecture, University of Pittsburgh, manuscript, 1960 (Box 80, Folder 22)
    - "Social Class Influences Upon Learning," Intergroup Education Institute, manuscripts, 1966 (Box 80, Folder 23)
    - "Social Studies and the Negro Community," Lincoln University, manuscript, undated (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - "Testing Program for the Disadvantaged Youth," Broward County Board of Public Instruction, manuscripts, agenda, notes, 1966 (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - "The Transition From Adolescence to Young Adulthood," Virgil Herrick Memorial Lecture, University of Wisconsin, manuscripts, 1973 (Box 81, Folder 3)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 81, Folder 4)
    - Untitled, Los Angeles, culture and variation, partial manuscript, notes, undated (Box 81, Folder 5)
    - Untitled, Ohio County [West Virginia] Education Association, speech on change in society and schools, partial manuscript, program, notes, 1967 (Box 81, Folder 6)
    - Untitled, University of Chicago, Rockefeller Chapel Memorial in honor of the Jackson State College Students, manuscript, correspondence, notes, 1970 (Box 81, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, University of Nebraska Home Economics Association, speech on deprivation, transcript, notes, 1969 [note: also Arizona State University, Minnesota Teachers Association] (Box 81, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 6: Fiction
    - ["King Victor"], manuscripts, notes, 1971 (Box 81, Folder 9)
    - Old Man, Young Woman, notes for novel, [includes "Yolanda"], undated (Box 81, Folder 10)
    - Strickland and the Unknown World, novel, manuscripts, notes, 1934-1983 (Box 82, Folder 1-9)
- Series VII: Audio Tapes
  The materials contained in this series are restricted due to their physical condition or the need for special equipment.
  This series contains tape and cassette recordings of lectures and addresses by Davis. These tapes have been identified using those markings available on the reel or tape box. Most are class lectures, with some public lectures as well, including the Leo Franklin Lecture at Wayne State University. There is also at least one example of a taped interview. Fifteen tapes are unidentified.
  - Best on Chester and Marge, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 1)
  - Best on Ego and conflict, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 2)
  - Defense mechanism, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 3)
  - Dora, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 4)
  - Ego and defense, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 5)
  - Ego and Id, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 6)
  - Freud and love, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 7)
  - Luther, 7" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 8)
  - Zacharias' conference, 7" reel, 1963 (Box 83, Reel 9)
  - B. Kae Johnson #148, Liddie's Interview, 7" reel, 1959 (Box 83, Reel 10)
  - Recess at a Chicago school: games of kindergarteners, recorded by Catherine Hughes, 5" reel, undated (Box 83, Reel 11)
  - Arizona State University, cassette, 1969 (Box 83, Cassette 1)
  - Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University, Summer Institute, "Standardized Tests and the Educability of the Negro," "Graduate Research in Education and Psychology," address, 7" reels, 1964 (Box 84, Reel 1-3)
  - Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University, FAMU Playmakers, "A Slave with Two Faces," play, 3" reel, 1964 (Box 84, Reel 4)
  - Wayne State University, Leo Franklin Lecture, "Sociological Dimensions of Group Membership," address, 7" reel, one missing tape, 1966 (Box 84, Reel 5)
  - Wayne State University, "Identity [in Adolescence and Young Adulthood]," 7" reel, ca. 1966 (Box 84, Reel 6)
  - Unidentified, 7" reels, undated (Box 84, Reel 7-12)
  - Unidentified, 7" reels, undated (Box 85, Reel 1-7)
  - Unidentified, 4" reel, undated (Box 85, Reel 8)
  - Unidentified, 2" reel, undated (Box 85, Reel 9)
  - Unidentified, scraps, undated (Box 85, Reel 10)
- Series VIII: Letters of Recommendation and Nomination
  Series VIII is restricted and will not be open for research until 2024.
  This small series primarily contains letters of reference, as well as several folders of nomination materials from the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
  - Letters of reference, grant evaluation, 1961-1974 (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Committee on Membership, nominations, 1969-1974 (Box 86, Folder 2-4)